So yesterday, I was out in the street
بالامس. كنت خارجا في الشارع
in front of this building,
أمام هذا المبنى
and I was walking down the sidewalk,
و كنت امشي على الرصيف
and I had company, several of us,
و كان معي رفقة, مجموعة منا,
and we were all abiding by the rules
و كنا جميعا ملتزمون بالقاعدة
of walking down sidewalks.
بأن نمشي على الرصيف
We're not talking each other. We're facing forward.
لم نكن نتحدث مع بعضنا البعض. كنا ننظر للأمام.
We're moving.
نحن متحركين
When the person in front of me slows down.
عندما قام الشخص الذي أمامي بالتخفيف من سرعته.
And so I'm watching him, and he slows down,
و أنا انظر اليه و هو يفعل ذلك
and finally he stops.
و في النهاية توقف تماما
Well, that wasn't fast enough for me,
حسنا, هذا لم يكن بالسرعة الكافية بالنسبة لي,
so I put on my turn signal, and I walked around him,
فقمت باشارة الانعطاف, و مشيت حوله,
and as I walked, I looked to see what he was doing,
و بينما أنا أمشي, نظرت لارى ماذا يفعل
and he was doing this.
و قد كا يفعل الاني.
He was texting,
كان يرسل باستخدام هاتفه,
and he couldn't text and walk at the same time.
ولم يستطع الكتابة و المشي في نفس الوقت.
Now we could approach this
الان نستطيع ان نقول الاتي
from a working memory perspective
من منظور الذاكرة العاملة
or from a multitasking perspective.
أو من منظور تعدد المهام.
We're going to do working memory today.
-- سنقوم بالذكرة العاملة اليوم --
Now, working memory
الان, الذاكرة العاملة
is that part of our consciousness that we are
هي الجزء من وعينا التي
aware of at any given time of day.
نعرفها في أي وقت من اليوم
You're going it right now.
انتم تفعلونها الان.
It's not something we can turn off.
انها ليست شيئا نستطبع ايقافه.
If you turn it off, that's called a coma, okay?
اذا اوقفتها, فانها تسمى غيبوبة, حسنا؟
So right now, you're doing just fine.
اذا الان, انتم بخير
Now working memory has four basic components.
الذاكرة العاملة لها اربعة مكونات اساسية.
It allows us to store some immediate experiences
فهي تسمح لنا بحفظ بعض الخبرات اللحظية
and a little bit of knowledge.
و القليل من المعرفة.
It allows us to reach back into our long-term memory
و تسمح لنا بالوصول الى ذاكرتنا طويلة المدى
and pull some of that in as we need it,
و سحب جزء منها عندما نحتاج,
mixes it, processes it
تخلطه و تعالجه
in light of whatever our current goal is.
على ضوء اهدافنا الحالية.
Now the current goal isn't something like,
الان الاهداف الحالية ليست شيئا مثل,
I want to be president or the best surfer in the world.
اريد ان اكون رئيسا, او افضل راكب امواج في العالم.
It's more mundane. I'd like that cookie,
انها اكثر عادية. مثل "اريد تلك الكعكة"
or I need to figure out how to get into my hotel room.
او اريد ان اعرف كيف أصل الى غرفتي في الفندق
Now working memory capacity
الان سعة الذاكرة العاملة
is our ability to leverage that,
هي قدرتنا على تنفيذ ذلك,
our ability to take what we know
أو قدرتنا على اخذ ما نعرف
and what we can hang onto
و ما نتمسك به
and leverage it in ways that allow us to satisfy
و تنفيذه بالطرق التى تجعلنا نشبع
our current goal.
اهدافنا الحالية
Now working memory capacity
الان سعة الذاكرة العاملة
has a fairly long history,
لها مدى طويل نسبيا,
and it's associated with a lot of positive effects.
و هي مرتبطة بالعديد من التاثيرات الايجابية
People with high working memory capacity
الاشخاص الذين يملكون ذاكرة فعالة ذات سعة عالية
tend to be good storytellers.
عادة يكونون جيدين في رواية القصص
They tend to solve and do well on standardized tests,
و يستطيعون حل و يعملون جيدا في الاختبارات القياسية
however important that is.
مع ان هذا مهم
They're able to have high levels of writing ability.
يكونون قادرين على امتلاك قدرة عالية على الكتابة
They're also able to reason at high levels.
ويستطيعون ان يقوموا بالنقاش المنطقي بدرجة عالية
So what we're going to do here is play a little bit with some of that.
اذا, ما سنفعله هنا هو ان نلعب بذلك قليلا
So I'm going to ask you to perform a couple tasks,
ساطلب منكن ان تقوموا ببعض المهمات,
and we're going to take your working memory out for a ride.
و سنأخذ ذاكرتكم العاملة في جولة.
You up for that? Okay.
هل مستعدون لذلك؟ حسنا.
I'm going to give you five words,
سأعطيكم خمس كلمات,
and I just want you to hang on to them.
و أريدكم فقط أن تحتفظوا بهم.
Don't write them down. Just hang on to them.
لا تكتبوهم. فقط احتفظوا بهم.
Five words.
خمس كلمات.
While you're hanging on to them, I'm going to ask you to answer three questions.
بينما انتم محتفظين بهم, سوف أطلب منكم أن تجيبوا على ثلاثة اسئلة.
I want to see what happens with those words.
أريد أن ارى ما سيحدث مع هذه الكلمات.
So here's the words:
اذا ها هي الكلمات:
tree,
شجرة"tree"
highway,
طريق سريع"highway"
mirror,
مرآة"mirror"
Saturn
كوكب زحل"Saturn"
and electrode.
قطب كهربائي"electrode"
So far so good?
جيد حتى الان؟
Okay. What I want you to do
حسنا. ما اريدكم أن تفعلوه
is I want you to tell me what the answer is
هو ان تخبروني ما هي الاجابة
to 23 times eight.
ل 23 مضروبة في 8
Just shout it out.
فقط قولوها بصوت عالي
(Mumbling) (Laughter)
(تمتمة) (ضحك)
In fact it's -- (Mumbling) -- exactly. (Laughter)
في الحقيقة هي -- (تمتمة) بالظبط -- (ضحك)
All right. I want you to take out your left hand
حسنا, اريكم أن تخرجوا يدكم اليسرى
and I want you to go, "One, two, three, four, five,
وتفعلوا, "واحد, اثنين, ثلاثة, اربعة, خمسة,
six, seven, eight, nine, 10."
ستة, سبعة, ثمانية, تسعة, عشرة."
It's a neurological test, just in case you were wondering.
انه اختبار عصبي, في حالة كنتم مستغربين.
All right, now what I want you to do
حسنا, الان ما اريدكم ان تفعلوه
is to recite the last five letters
هو ان تسردوا الحروف الخمسة الاخيرة
of the English alphabet backwards.
في الاحرف الهجائية الانجليزية بالعكس
You should have started with Z.
من المفتروض أن تبدْوا لحرف "z"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All right. How many people here are still pretty sure
حسنا, كم منكم مازال متأكدا
you've got all five words?
انهم يتذكرون الخمس كلمات؟
Okay. Typically we end up with about less than half,
حسنا, عادة ننتهي بأقل من النصف,
right, which is normal. There will be a range.
وهذا طبيعي. سيكون هناك مدى
Some people can hang on to five.
البعض يستطيع الاحتفاظ بالخمس.
Some people can hang on to 10.
البعض يستطيع الاحتفاظ حتى 10.
Some will be down to two or three.
البعض سيكون حتى 2 أو 3
What we know is this is really important to the way we function, right?
ما نعرفه ان هذا مهم جدا للطريقة التي نعمل بها, ايس كذلك؟
And it's going to be really important here at TED
و سيكون مهما جدا هنا في TED.
because you're going to be exposed to so many different ideas.
لانكم ستتعرضون لعدد كبير من الافكار.
Now the problem that we have
الان المشكلة التي تواجهنا
is that life comes at us,
ان الحياة تاتي نحونا
and it comes at us very quickly,
و تاتي بسرعة شديدة,
and what we need to do is to take that amorphous
و علينا ان ناخذ هذا الفيض غير المتبلور
flow of experience and somehow
من الخبرة و بشكل ما
extract meaning from it
نستخرج منه معنى
with a working memory
باستخدام الذاكرة العاملة
that's about the size of a pea.
والتي بحجم حبة بازلاء
Now don't get me wrong, working memory is awesome.
الان لا تسيئوا فهمي, الذاكرة العاملة رائعة.
Working memory allows us
الذاكرة العاملة تسمح لنا
to investigate our current experience
بالتحقيق في خبراتنا الحالية
as we move forward.
و نحن متحركين للامام
It allows us to make sense of the world around us.
و تسمح لنا بان نفهم العالم من حولنا.
But it does have certain limits.
ولكن لديها حدود معينة.
Now working memory is great for allowing us to communicate.
الان الذاكرة العاملة رائعة في جعلنا نتواصل
We can have a conversation,
نستطيع ان نجري حوارات,
and I can build a narrative around that
نستطيع ان نبني قصة حولها
so I know where we've been and where we're going
فانا اعرف اين كنا و اين سنذهب
and how to contribute to this conversation.
و كيف اشارك في هذا الحوار
It allows us to problem-solve, critical think.
تسمح لنا بحل المشاكل, بالتفكير النقدي.
We can be in the middle of a meeting,
نستطيع ان نكون في منتصف اجتماع,
listen to somebody's presentation, evaluate it,
نستمع الى عرض شخص ما, تقييمه,
decide whether or not we like it,
و تقرير اذا اعجبنا أم لا,
ask follow-up questions.
و نسأل أسئلة متابعة.
All of that occurs within working memory.
كل هذا يحدث داخل الذاكرة العاملة .
It also allows us to go to the store
تسمح لنا ان نذهب الى المتجر
and allows us to get milk and eggs and cheese
و نجلب الحليب و البيض و الجبن
when what we're really looking for
عندما يكون ما نبحث عنه
is Red Bull and bacon. (Laughter)
هو مشروب "Red Bull" و اللحم المقدد (ضحك)
Gotta make sure we're getting what we're looking for.
لابد ان نتاكد ان نحصل على ما نبحث عنه
Now, a central issue with working memory
الان, مسألة مركزية بالنسبة للذاكرة العاملة
is that it's limited.
انها محدودة.
It's limited in capacity, limited in duration,
محدودة السعة, محدودة المدة,
limited in focus.
محدودة التركيز.
We tend to remember about four things.
نميل أن نركز على اربعة اشاء.
Okay? It used to be seven,
حسنا؟ كانت في الاصل سبعة,
but with functional MRIs, apparently it's four,
و لكن مع التصوير بالرنين المغنطيسي "MRI", تبين انها اربعة
and we were overachieving.
و نحن اعلى انجازا
Now we can remember those four things
الان نستطيع ان نتذكر هذه الاربعة اشياء
for about 10 to 20 seconds
لمدة 10 الى 20 ثانية
unless we do something with it,
الا اذا فعلنا بها شيئا
unless we process it, unless we apply it to something,
الا اذا عالجناها, او طبقناها على شيء ما,
unless we talk to somebody about it.
الا اذا تحدثنا عنها الى شخص ما.
When we think about working memory,
عندما نتحدث عن الذاكرة العاملة
we have to realize that this limited capacity
لقد وجدنا ان هذه السعة المحدودة
has lots of different impacts on us.
لديها العديد من التاثيرات علينا.
Have you ever walked from one room to another
هل حدث ان ذهبت من عرفة الى اخرى
and then forgotten why you're there?
و من ثم نسيت لماذا انت هنا؟
You do know the solution to that, right?
انت تعرف الحل لذلك, اليس كذلك؟
You go back to that original room. (Laughter)
ان تعود الى الغرفة الاولى. (ضحك)
Have you ever forgotten your keys?
هل نسيت مفاتيحك من قبل؟
You ever forgotten your car?
هل نسيت سيارتك؟
You ever forgotten your kids?
هل نسيت اطفالك؟
Have you ever been involved in a conversation,
هل كنت في منتصف محادثة من قبل,
and you realize that the conversation to your left
و انتبهت ان المحادثة الى يسارك
is actually more interesting? (Laughter)
في الحقيقة اكثر اثارة للاهتمام؟ (ضحك)
So you're nodding and you're smiling,
فاصبحت تشير براسك و تبتسم,
but you're really paying attention to this one over here,
و في الحقيقة انت منتبه الى المحادثة الاخرى
until you hear that last word go up,
الى ان تسمع اخر كلمة تفال
and you realize,
و تنتبه
you've been asked a question. (Laughter)
انك قد سئلت سؤالا. (ضحك)
And you're really hoping the answer is no,
و تامل أن تكون الاجابة بلا,
because that's what you're about to say.
لان ذلك هو ما انت بصدد قوله.
All of that talks about working memory,
كل هذا يتحدث عن الذاكرة العاملة ,
what we can do and what we can't do.
ما نستطيع فعله و ما لانستطيع فعله.
We need to realize that working memory
لا بد ان نعرف ان الذاكرة العاملة
has a limited capacity,
لها سعة محدودة,
and that working memory capacity itself is how we negotiate that.
و سعة الذاكرة المحددة هي نفسها الطريقة الني نناقش فيها ذلك.
We negotiate that through strategies.
نناقش ذلك عبر الاستراتيجيات.
So what I want to do is talk a little bit about a couple of strategies here,
اذا ما اريد الحديث عنه قليلا هو عدد من الاستراتيجيات,
and these will be really important
و هذا سيكون مهما جدا
because you are now in an information target-rich environment
لانكم الان في بيئة غنية بالمعلومات
for the next several days.
في الايام القليلة القادمة.
Now the first part of this that we need to think about
الان اول جزء نحتاج ان نفكر فيه
and we need to process our existence, our life,
و نحتاج ان نعالج وجودنا, حياتنا,
immediately and repeatedly.
فورا و باستمرار
We need to process what's going on
نحتاج ان نعالج ما يحدث
the moment it happens, not 10 minutes later,
في لحظة حدوثه و ليس بعد 10 دقائق,
not a week later, at the moment.
ليس بعد اسبوع, بل في اللحظة.
So we need to think about, well, do I agree with him?
اذا نحتاج ان نفكر, "حسنا, هل اوافقه؟
What's missing? What would I like to know?
ما الشيء الناقص؟ ماذا اود ان اعرف؟
Do I agree with the assumptions?
هل اوافق على هذا الافتراض؟
How can I apply this in my life?
كيف استطيع ان اطبق ذلك في حياتي؟"
It's a way of processing what's going on
انها طريقة لمعالجة ما يحدث
so that we can use it later.
حتى نستطيع استخدامه لاحقا.
Now we also need to repeat it. We need to practice.
الان نحتاج الى تكراره. نحتاج الى التمرين.
So we need to think about it here.
اذا نحتاج ان نفكر فيه هنا.
In between, we want to talk to people about it.
في المنتصف, نريد ان نتحدث عنه مع الناس.
We're going to write it down, and when you get home,
سوف نقوم بكتابته, و عندما نذهب الى البيت
pull out those notes and think about them
تخرج هذه الملاحظات و نفكر فيها
and end up practicing over time.
و ينتهي بنا الامر بالتمرين مع الزمن.
Practice for some reason became a very negative thing.
التمرين و لسبب ما اصبح شيئا سالبا جدا.
It's very positive.
انه شيء ايجابي.
The next thing is, we need to think elaboratively
الشيء التالي, نحتاج ان نفكر باسهاب
and we need to think illustratively.
و نحتاج ان نفكر باسلوف تفسيري.
Oftentimes, we think that we have to relate new knowledge to prior knowledge.
في بعض الاحيان, نعتقد انه علينا ربط المعرفة الجديدة بمعرفة سابقة.
What we want to do is spin that around.
و الذي نريد ان نفعله هو ان نعكس ذلك تماما.
We want to take all of our existence
نريد ان ناخذ وجودنا ككل
and wrap it around that new knowledge
و نضعه حول تلك المعرفة الجديدة
and make all of these connections and it becomes more meaningful.
و نقوم بكل تلك الارتباطات و سيصبح ذو معنى
We also want to use imagery. We are built for images.
نحتاج ايضا ان نستخدم التصوير. نحن مبنيون على الصور.
We need to take advantage of that.
لابد ان نستغل ذلك.
Think about things in images,
فكر في الاشياء على شكل صور,
write things down that way.
و اكتبها على هذه الطريقة.
If you read a book, pull things up.
اذا قرات كتابا, استخرج بعض الاشياء.
I just got through reading "The Great Gatsby,"
لقد انتهيت من قراءة "The Great Gatsby"
and I have a perfect idea of what he looks like
و لدي فكرة كاملة عن شكله
in my head, so my own version.
في راسي, نسختي الخاصة.
The last one is organization and support.
الشيء الاخير هو التنظيم و الدعم.
We are meaning-making machines. It's what we do.
نحن الات لصنع المعنى. هذا ما نفعله
We try to make meaning out of everything that happens to us.
نحاول ان نجعل لكل شيء يحدث لنا معنى.
Organization helps, so we need to structure
التنظيم يساعدنا, اذا نحتاج الى هيكلة
what we're doing in ways that make sense.
ما نفعله بطريقة تجعل له معنى.
If we are providing knowledge and experience,
اذا كنا نقدم المعرفة و الخبرة,
we need to structure that.
لابد ان نضع لها هيكلة.
And the last one is support.
والاخيرة هي الدعم.
We all started as novices.
كلنا بدأنا مبتدئين.
Everything we do is an approximation of sophistication.
كل ما نفعله هو تقريب من التطور.
We should expect it to change over time. We have to support that.
ولابد ان نتوقع ان يتغير مع الزمن. لابد ان ندعم ذلك.
The support may come in asking people questions,
الدعم يمكن ان يكون بان نسأل الناس اسئلة,
giving them a sheet of paper that has an organizational chart on it
نعطيهم قطعة من الورق بها هيكل تنظيمي
or has some guiding images,
او بعض الرسومات التوضيحية,
but we need to support it.
ولكن لابد ان ندعم ذلك.
Now, the final piece of this, the take-home message
الان, القطعة الاخيرة, الرسالة التي ناخذها معنا الى البيت
from a working memory capacity standpoint is this:
من وجهة نظر سعة الذاكرة العاملة :
what we process, we learn.
ما نعالجه, نتعلمه.
If we're not processing life, we're not living it.
اذا لم نقم بمعالجة الحياة, فنحن لا نعيشها.
Live life. Thank you.
عيشوا حياتكم. شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)